Bursting onto the scene only 5 short years ago
Valorant was a game that was perfectly poised to
to become a competitive Esports mainstay.
Blending elements from the popular hero shooters at the time
With the tactical skill of the precision shooters that came before it,
It offered opportunity for those with skill and creativity in equal measure.
And while there's a lot that could be said about Valorant's
place in the gaming community,
Anyone who follows this channel knows I don't really make videos about games,
I make videos about people.
And while there are hundreds of people within the Valorant community
that have interesting stories to share,
There's one that perfectly covers not what Valorant is or has become,
But everything that it could be.
A story about a competitor with flair.
A teammate with resilience and toughness.
A young man chasing a dream.
So join me on the Deep Dive as we examine the compelling rise
and tragic legacy
of Twisten.
[ 🎵 SOMBER PIANO NOTES FADE IN🎵]
At a young age, Karel Ašenbrener engaged in many of the same activities
that any child in Czechia would.
However, being born during the boom of the digital age
and having two older brothers,
Karel would find a love for gaming very early on.
Ultimately taking to counterstrike and the CS:GO scene that followed,
He wasn't even a teenager the first time he participated in a live LAN competition.
A few years later when Rainbow 6 was released in 2015,
His love for the game propelled him even deeper into the competitive scene.
And as his skills and nuanced knowledge developed,
2019 would see them refined enough to land
him a spot on the fledgling Dark Tigers roster
For what he hoped would be his first step on the road to Esports greatness...
as Twisten
Proving himself a standout in the smaller EMEA market,
he would play for the Dark Tigers for only 3 months
before making the switch to Cyber Gaming to continue his journey.
As Twisten was building up a head of steam going into 2020,
the unfortunate timing of the pandemic would sweep across the globe and halt
pretty much any hope for regional competition.
By March of that year, his dream of playing at the absolute
peak level of competition had fully stalled,
and his dream of playing on the world's biggest stage was entirely on hold.
For what must have been an agonizing few months
Twisten likely spent a great deal of his time looking
to fight of the boredom of being locked inside.
And on June 2nd of 2020,
the universe decided to throw him a lifeline.
Finding Valorant to be a perfect blend of his skills from CS:GO
with the role-based team play of Rainbow 6 Seige,
Twisten took to Valorant with Incredible ease.
And only 3 months after the game's release, Twisten would be competing once more
after being scouted to join the newly created Kings of Sosnovka.
The team struggled to find success...
But, when the team was rebranded to Esuba just a couple short months later,
2 things had already been made perfectly clear.
First, Twisten was clearly a powerhouse that was capable
of edging out the impact of his opponents,
and 2, Twisten wasn't interested in slowing down until he reached the absolute top.
So after months of delivering huge plays and massive numbers,
and with Riot announcing the kickoff of an official
competitive tour towards the end of 2020,
Twisten knew that he'd be looking to partner with a team
that was seeking success on an international stage.
So when Entropiq was looking for the last piece of the puzzle to fill out their roster,
conditions were perfect for Twisten to take a shot at the next tier of competition.
Entropiq would start 2021 strong by taking a second place finish
in the Versus Legends Invitational before stage 1 even began.
From there, their first chance to qualify for Masters would see great success.
As they battled their way out of group stages and continued their run
until falling just short of qualifying against a sturdy Guild Esports
Unfortunately, despite battling past the competition to enter qualifiers consistently...
Entropiq's next 2 attempts to secure a ticket to masters for the VCT's
inaugural season were dashed, with little room for optimism.
With Entropiq having recently made a significant investment in their new Valorant
Esports effort by securing for Overwatch League pros HyP and Taimo,
the lack of success proved concerning.
And before the team could even attempt to right the ship during stage 3,
Entropiq pulled the plug
and announced their were dissolving their Valorant division entirely.
Twisten was now without a home,
and had yet to taste victory on an international stage.
He knew it was time for a big leap, and playing it safe simply wouldn't do anymore.
So, with numerous orgs looking to add his massive potential to their roster,
he packed his bags and traveled to Berlin, to sign with BIG Clan Esports.
While it would seem on the surface that absolutely everything was going his way,
and he had every reason to be optimistic about the future,
Twisten would reveal that his true fight
wasn't taking place on stage in front of the cameras.
Even despite his incredible dedication,
and proving he could excel against tougher opponents in the off-season,
He was continuing to fall behind in the fight for his mental health.
Struggling with self-doubt, far away from home,
and putting everything he had into making his dream come true,
the mental strain was weighing heavily on the young rising star.
And while it's reasonable to think that after joining a new team
outside of his home country,
after the implosion of his previous org,
and all before his 18th birthday would likely cause any player
to need a small window of time to adjust.
But Twisten wasn't just any player,
and giving everything he had to win...
Didn't require any adjustment at all.
Commentator: "Twisten just popping heads as they go"
"Twisten! So annoying to play against this guy. Who does that!?"
"... a solution to the problem __ BUT TWISTEN'S GOT'EM"
"Twisten's on it and he's an absolute beast"
"Now... oh oh... Twisten! This could be big..."
"There's just no way he should be able to get away with that"
"Almost too easy and... How is Twisten winning these battles?"
XDeej: After a flawless run in open qualifiers,
and then finishing second in the closed qualifiers,
BIG was looking to make a run in group stages
that would punch their ticket to the playoffs.
Unfortunately, against the highest level of competition,
BIG would struggle to seal the deal.
Despite their execution to this point, the group stages would prove a hill
too tall to climb for such an underdog team.
And after failing to secure even a single win in the group stages,
BIG's hopes for a shot at Masters would have to wait until stage 2.
And while they would show improvement, it was still far too little,
and would see them denied a spot in the playoffs once more.
As they geared up to take on the challenge of last-chance qualifiers,
Riot made an announcement that would change the future of the VCT...
and would throw Twisten's future within it, into question.
Instead of their existing format of open regional tournaments
that provide a chance for any team to go on a miracle run,
Riot would now be selecting partner teams
that would hold a persistent place at the top.
Much like the structure of the Overwatch and Call of Duty leagues,
selected teams were chosen based on their track record, size,
popularity, and their ability to grow the Esport across the globe.
While Riot certainly can't be faulted for wanting to give the VCT
the best chance to reach the widest possible audience,
that means that small market teams like BIG only had a slim chance
to be selected for one of the limited spaces assigned to each region.
And when going up against organizations
with massive followings that had been around for decades,
BIG's future in the VCT was anything but guaranteed.
And with Twisten's fate in the league tied to BIG's success,
even his standout performances couldn't carry BIG far up enough the ranks
to stand out from the highly competitive crowd.
And when the Riot partner teams were announced on September 21st,
Twisten could only hope that he had done enough
to draw the attention from the lucky teams that had been chosen.
Thinking Man's Valorant: "You can kind of understand because
You know, if there's a good German player, y'know, like Twisten for instance from BIG
Yeah, he's probably gonna end up on one of these teams anyway, right?
Despite BIG not being selected to represent the VCT at the international level,
Twisten leading his team to an 18-3 record
would prove enough to catch the eye of Team Vitality.
And after joining the roster of a Riot partner team
with far more funding and resources,
He was as close as he had ever been to achieving his dream.
Knowing how rare this opportunity was...
Twisten would make sure to use every match to prove he was up to the task.
Commentator 1: "The shorty comes out... it doesn't
Commentator 2:
Commentator 1: WAAAIT!!! He's done this with 50 HP!!
Commentator 2: WHAT!?
Commentator 2: WHAT!? WHAT!?!?
Commentator 1: "TWISTEN! And what goes on in this man's brain!?"
Commentator 1: "Moves now, ended up..."
Commentator 2:
Commentator 2: "Lunatic"
Commentator 1: "Moves now, ended up... with a pistol"
Commentator 1: "Twisten's just pushed in"
Commentator 2: "Lunatic"
Commentator 2: "WHAT!?"
Commentator 1: "In his own wall!"
Commentator 1: "He peeks into the speed lane and just gets a double for it."
Commentator 1: "...Means it's shorty time"
Commentator 1: "He's gonna get close!"
Commentator 1: "Cloud bursts all around"
Commentator 1: "They don't know where he is and now they found him."
Commentator 2 [heavy laughing]
Commentator 2 [heavy laughing] "What??"
Commentator 1: "The way his brain works, it's just an absurdity."
Commentator 2: "The confidence of this man...
Commentator 2: "2 kills within the first 15 second of the round."
XDeej: Going into the new season format,
Twisten had proven to be a crowd favorite for 2 main reasons.
the first, was that he had the charisma, spirit, and character that drew people in.
And second, there was no one more terrifying to play against in close quarters.
Commentator 1: "Page number 1 in the anti-strat book for these guys:
Commentator 1: "Twisten plays the shorty"
Commentor 2: "Don't you DARE!"
Commentor 1:
Commentor 1: [heavy laughing]
Commentor 2: "Like, what are you supposed to do against this guy?"
Commentor 1: "oh god..."
XDeej: So with Riot announcing that the first international major was actually
going to be a winner take all single-elimination tournament in Sao Paulo Brazil,
simply being the forefather of the shorty meta wasn't good enough.
And with the opening shot of the 2023 season behind him,
he would pack his bags,
and travel with Vitality to what would be his first international major... ever.
And while he had never faced such stiff competition,
he had already proven that he could compete with the best Europe could offer,
and now it was time to make a name for himself on Valorant's biggest stage.
With nerves as high as they could get, and with the whole world watching,
Twisten would truly show what he was made of.
While small hang-ups at a team level would send Vitality home
after a disappointing 1 and 1 performance,
The tournament provided a *lot* of insight into Twisten's future.
One of the main takeaways in that tournament was that with over 160 players,
representing the absolute best in the world,
Twisten would finish with an Average Combat Score [ACS] of 263.
Which would be good enough to put him in 4th place, including all in attendance.
And while Vitality were leaving sooner than they would have liked,
Twisten's pledge to donate 25 Euros for each kill with the shorty at the tournament
was being taken to heart with all the competitors in the field.
And after leading the way in showing what it could do,
it seems like the secret was out,
and it was being used now more than ever.
And Twisten wasn't just succeeding in-game.
His flashy style and aggressive play would also win over many of the attendants.
So, while the end result provided limited room to be disappointed,
The tournament was widely considered to be a success for Vitality,
and a HUGE win for Twisten.
And perhaps that would have been the takeaway...
If there were any truth to it below the surface.
But in actuality,
Twisten's world wasn't as bright as it had seemed.
In his limited time with Team Vitality,
He had already earned the role of practical joker,
Team cheerleader,
and the first one in line to provide support if you were having a tough time.
But while he was busy being there for others,
Twisten's mental health had only gotten worse.
And despite his excellent performance at his first international major,
He would return home, and take to Twitter to outline just how difficult things had been.
In addition to an emergency 3-day hospital stay over Christmas,
Twisten had been dealing with the byproduct of being a public figure
all the way back to his time playing with BIG.
With the absolute worst of the internet often reaching out
to personally make his condition worse.
The Sao Paulo tournament was the first in weeks that he'd go without wearing
long sleeves, even in the practice room,
to avoid anyone knowing how difficult his recent depression had been.
But in addition to opening up about the struggles he faced,
he also used the opportunity to praise his organization and teammates
for their unwavering support.
He carved out a separate segment to encourage others to seek help if they need it.
and while there was no doubting the challenges directly behind him,
Twisten also made sure to mention that thanks to the dedication
and support from his team, he was now in a great place,
and looked forward to leading Vitality to an incredible year.
While the revelations were a shock to many in the community,
the fanbase that Vitality had cultivated,
and the respect that Twisten had earned from his fellow competitors in the scene,
resulted in an outpouring of support that would only bolster his resolve
and commitment to the upcoming season.
And with his mental health struggles out in the public,
and his team and fans remaining behind him 100 percent,
Twisten and company set their sights on the second opportunity
to make it to the champions tournament.
And while Twisten would produce another top 10 performance in the league,
over the course of the regular season,
Vitality would just barely scrape by with a 6th place finish in the league,
to qualify for the last seed in the group stage playoffs.
And after losing their first playoff match to Team Liquid,
and then losing a close 2 to 1 split in the loser's bracket quarter finals,
Team Vitality would fail to move forward.
and Twisten would once against fall just short
of reaching the next peak in front of him.
And with that...
Vitality's season would come to an abrupt and unfortunate end.
While they could certainly go on to make one more attempt on the season
in the last chance qualifiers.
Their most recent loss would prove insignificant
in comparison to what would be lost shortly after.
On the morning of June 7th, 2023,
It was announced that Karel "Twisten" Ašenbrener
had died
as the result of an apparent su*.
He was 19 years old.
[🎵 INTO DIAMOND SKIES 🎵]
[🎵 LETTING MEMORIES GO 🎵]
XDeej: It's often said that those with the biggest smiles often hide the deepest pain.
And now the man widely considered by many to be the kindest,
most caring, and uniquely loving people in the scene, would shine his light no more.
The hole that was left in the community would never be filled.
And the loss felt by his friends, family, teammates, and fans, was beyond measure.
In the wake of his tragic passing,
Team Vitality would choose to forego any additional play in the VCT that year.
Both to allow their players, staff, and coaches time to grieve...
But also because of the unique challenge
of trying to fill a seat that could never truly be filled.
In the grand finals match of the Master's tournament that followed,
both teams would open the first round of competition with a joust,
using only the short to honor their fallen brother.
Commentator: "This was their decision.
uhh, this was not something that production said 'hey we should do this',
they decided on their own and actually..."
Riot would add a title in the following season
able to be unlocked by all, to keep his spirit alive in-game.
And following time to grieve and recover,
His mother would go on to found the Twisten Foundation,
An entirely non-profit organization dedicated
to helping individuals who suffer from depression.
You can find a link to the foundation's website in the description below.
And as for me, I've spent the last month investigating a life lost too soon.
Looking at his childhood pictures, exploring his history,
and the only conclusion I can come to is this world would be a better place
with more people like Twisten in it.
Do make sure to like and subscribe if you'd like to see more important
stories like this brought to the channel in the future,
and remember to share around to help keep Twisten's legacy alive.
And with that I believe my job here is done,
and until I see you next time,
take care of yourselves,
and each other.
[🎵 INTO DIAMOND SKIES 🎵]